Good morning. And the mic for the recorder seems to be missing
also. I
don't think he's been using the mic.
Okay. Good morning everyone.
Today is January 25th, it's the ninth of שבט. Shevat. I'm Dan
Margulies, I'm filling in
for Rabbi Linzer, he's
unavailable this morning because
one version said he had
to go
to a ברית, Bris, another version said he had to go pay
a שבעה Shiva call, but either way our
thoughts and hearts are with him while he's not here and we'll
continue the learning without him. We'll pick up from the last line
of ט עמוד ב Tet Amud Bet getting into the close of
some of these discussions about שטר Shtar and dating and things like
that and then we're going to get into some אגדתא Agadata today
about the Roman emperor אנטונינוס Antoninus and his relationship with רבי יהודה
הנשיא. Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi. I mentioned before I started recording this is
like know your Roman emperors. I think for certain bits of Talmudic
literature
for sure having a reasonable grasp on Roman history certainly can help
us understand the political context and who are the important players. We
have to remember the Roman political structure as well. We'll get to
that when we get to it.
Who Marcus Aurelius really is?
This, so אנטונינוס Antoninus is the father of adoptive father of Marcus
Aurelius who will come up in the סוגיא. Sugya. Well Marcus Aurelius
actually doesn't appear in the סוגיא Sugya but the other other adoptive
son of אנטונינוס Antoninus does. Okay, from the last line of ט
עמוד ב. Tet Amud Bet. ההוא שטר דהוה כתיב ביה שית שנין
יתירתא. Hahu shtar dehavah kativ beih shit shanin yeterata. There was a
שטר, Shtar, there was a legal contract that was written with the
date six years seemingly six years in the future from the time
that it was being examined by the court. סבור רבנן קמיה דרבא
למימר האי שטר מאוחר הוא. Savor rabanan kamei deRava lemeimar hai shtar
meuchar hu.
So the rabbis who were in the presence of רבא Raba who
were assessing this case thought that it was a post-dated שטר. Shtar.
It was written with the date six years in advance so that
the liens couldn't be collected until six years from now. So they
said אנעכביה
עד דמטי זימניה, Anyakeivah ad demati zimneih, we should just hold it
back, we should restrict the use of the שטר Shtar to extract
the debt until the time comes ולא נפרע ביה Velo nifrah beih
and not to collect on it. אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman,
רב נחמן Rav Nachman says back האי ספרא דוכינא כתביה, Hai safra
dukina katveih, it was a skilled scribe, it was an elder of
the scribes who wrote this, that is he knew what he was
doing, he had a particular reason for it. It wasn't written as
a post-dated שטר, Shtar, it's actually written as a שטר Shtar for
now. והנך שית שנין דמלכו בעילם, Vahanach shit shanin demalku beEilam, these
six years when the Macedonian, the Greek empire ruled over עילם,
Eilam, עילם Eilam is somewhere in the Mesopotamia region, דאנן לא חשבינן
להו. Deanan lo chashvinan lehu. So when we count our מנין שטרות
Minyan Shtarot usually, our dating for documents, we don't use those extra
six years, we count from six years later in the rule of
Alexander the Great when his empire was really fully established. But this
scribe decided to include those six years, so it has nothing to
do with it being a post-dated שטר, Shtar, it was just a
different dating system.
There's a point by Rabbi Linzer in the reactions, not dating from
Alexander but from when the Seleucid
Empire started, a little bit after Alexander. Right. And it comes up
in our סוגיא Sugya as well, there's a suggestion we're going to
see the next סוגיא, Sugya, a suggestion that the dating is actually
from a thousand years after יציאת מצרים Yetziyat Mitzrayim and there's a,
that's the question, are we using a foreign date or are we
using a Jewish date? I know that I think it's Rabbi Yaakov
Medan at ישיבת הר עציון Yeshivat Har Etzion has like a certain
pet topic of his that he likes pushing counting the number of
years since יציאת מצרים, Yetziyat Mitzrayim, certainly that's how they counted the
years in תנ"ך, Tanakh, we see in references in the book of
שמואל Shmuel and places like that. Okay, so והנך שית שנין דמלכו
בעילם, Vahanach shit shanin demalku beEilam, these are the six years that
the Greeks ruled in עילם, Eilam, דאנן לא חשבינן להו. Deanan lo
chashvinan lehu. So he, this scribe who wrote this שטר Shtar decided
to count the years from six years earlier than we
do. הוא קחשיב להו, Hu kachashiv lehu, he counts those years ובזימניה
כתיב Uvezimneih kativ and the שטר Shtar is written in its own
time, it's written for right now. If you remember back I think
it's one of the first
more broadly applicable סוגיות Sugyot in גיטין, Gittin, I think it's around
גיטין דף י"ז Gittin Daf Yud Zayin or so there's a whole
discussion about writing a שטר מאוחר, Shtar meuchar, writing a שטר מוקדם,
Shtar mukdam, which kind of post-dated and pre-dated שטרות Shtarot are disqualified
or are okay to use. Obviously a predated שטר Shtar would be
invalid because what you're doing is you're retroactively claiming that the liens
are in place earlier than they are and what that does is
it undermines the ability of previously existing debtor claimants to claim property.
So that discussion is there in the first chapter of גיטין. Gittin.
Okay, דתניא רבי יוסי אומר שש שנים מלכו בעילם, De-tanya Rabbi Yosei
omer shesh shanim malchu be-Eilam, Rabbi Yosei says that the Greeks ruled
for six years in עילם Eilam ואחר כך פשטה מלכותן בכל העולם
כולו, ve-achar kach pashitah malchutan be-chol ha-olam kulo, and then their rule
spread out over the entire world. We know that the Macedonian Greeks,
I guess they're not Macedonian, they're just Greeks, they're from Macedonia, but
that... So the Greeks under Alexander and then under his heirs
fought many wars against the Persians, against the various other Eastern empires
that that meant that at what point do you claim that their
rule began? You have to pick some arbitrary point because they were
fighting many lengthy wars. So here's a debate: did they count those
six years or not? Okay, we see the next סוגיא Sugya is
going to be about יציאת מצרים. Yetziat Mitzrayim. מתקיף לה רב אחא
בר יעקב ממאי דמלכות יונים מנינן דילמא ליציאת מצרים מנינן. Matkif lah
Rav Acha bar Yaakov mi-mai de-malchut Yevanim mininan dilma li-Yetziat Mitzrayim mininan.
Maybe we do not count from the time of the Greeks, from
the Greek empires, but rather from
יציאת מצרים Yetziat Mitzrayim ושבקי לה אלפא קמא ונקטי,
ve-shavkei lah alfa kama ve-naktei, meaning like are we trying to say
that this is what the convention should be or
that's what the convention is? We know the year, the number of
the date. The question
is, right, how do we conceptualize the number of the year? For
example, in the United States, the Gregorian year, right, it's 2018.
So
some people say it's 2018 AD because they count according to the
birth of Jesus and some people say it's 2018 CE of the
Common Era because the conventional dating happens to be that it's 2018.
So we try to remove the Christological significance of that date as
Jews; we prefer a more secularized version of the same year. It's
something similar, which is when we say this year is 500 למנין
שטרות le-minyan shtarot or 800 למנין שטרות le-minyan shtarot or whatever, are
we counting and saying it's 500 years since the Seleucid dynasty or
are we saying it's 1,500 years since יציאת מצרים? Yetziat Mitzrayim?
Meaning you say it's a different year. You say 500...
Well, but so that's what the question... Because they say because the
question... Right, so the question is, but the question is, maybe for
convenience they left off the thousands place because they just count the
hundreds, right? When we say the year is
תשע"ח, Taf Shin Ayin Chet, we're not saying it's 578, we're saying
it's 5,000 whatever
778. But we're saying it's 5,778. We ignore the thousands place because
the thousands place only changes once every thousand years. Even the hundreds
place you might not have to, but sometimes you have to keep
track hundreds, something happened a hundred years ago is in more recent
memory. So that's part of what this question is.
It's funny because I don't know if we're going to address this,
we always get so worked up about החודש הזה לכם ראש חודשים.
ha-chodesh ha-zeh lachem rosh chodashim. Can you say one, one, whatever? No,
you can't, maybe because it should really... What?
To refer to the secular months by numbers?
I've heard some people
who are מקפיד makpid not to do that.
But what we're doing is, but if we say, but we seem
to have no problem with not having a conventional year, like we're
going by the Greek
whatever, like who... The point... any religious problem with that? It seems
not to be discussed at all where...
The passage of years is always a relative count. The things we
care about in terms of the passage of years are how long
did a king reign for, שמיטה, Shmita, יובל, Yovel, those sorts of
things. We don't care about an absolute time point in the count
of years until you get either Kabbalistic significance for it or you
get
people who try to date לבריאת העולם, le-vriat ha-olam, which seems not
to have been the convention at all in the medieval period even
for many of the medieval rabbis either. For some it was. So
you get whole discussions that obviously nowadays it's become conventional across most
Jewish communities to use... and even there we say למנין שאנו מונין
כאן. le-minyan she-anu monin kan.
Is there any problem with that?
I think they're saying... A conventional assessment for what is... So if
you would want to put in a שטר Shtar it's 2018 למנין
שאנו מונין כאן, le-minyan she-anu monin kan, I don't think it would
be a problem either, meaning because you'd say that's a conventional year
that we use now. There's no absolute meaning to the number of
years, just the months are important and which year it is is
important and we should know how many years have passed since some
previous event, but I don't think there's an absolute significance to the
number of years, obviously,
in terms of the גמרא Gemara as we saw at the end
of סנהדרין Sanhedrin thinking about oh, there's 6,000 years, there's 2,000 years
for תורה Torah and 2,000 years for משיח Mashiach and these kind
of things. So right, we had that come up here as well.
So there's
some... Right, we shouldn't be counting from the birth of Jesus explicitly
and even there, of all things, ספירת
הנוצרים.
Sephirat
HaNotzrim.
ספירת הנוצרים, Sephirat HaNotzrim, right, we don't even say, right. So, and
also for the Muslims. Okay, so let's get back into our סוגיא.
sugya. Okay, so מתקיף לה רב אחא בר יעקב. Matkif lah Rav
Acha bar Yaakov. So רב אחא בר יעקב Rav Acha bar Yaakov
challenged the whole assumption, implicit assumption that we should be counting by
מלכות יוונים. Malchut Yevanim. He says, ממאי דלמלכות יוונים מנינן? Mimai d'l'Malchut
Yevanim maninan?
Why are we counting or is it really true that we're counting
from the Greek years? דילמא ליציאת מצרים מנינן ושבקיה לאלפא קמא ונקטיה
אלפא בתרא,
Dilma l'Yitziat Mitzrayim maninan v'shavkia l'alfa kama v'naktia alfa
batra, ונקטיה אלפא בתרא? v'naktia alfa batra? So we took off the
first thousand years. So other interesting thing about this is that it's
the basic assumption is that we could date back that it's either
exactly or close to exactly a thousand years from יציאת מצרים Yitziat
Mitzrayim to the Seleucid Empire, which is more or less
right. יציאת מצרים Yitziat Mitzrayim seems to have taken place in the,
what is it, the 14th century BCE. Was it 14th? Or
the 13 something, 1330, 1312, I've heard things like that. So somewhere
around then, but it becomes helpful for thinking about when were דוד
ושלמה, David u'Shlomo, when... right, and we have archaeological evidence from בית
ראשון Bayit Rishon in Israel, which obviously helps corroborate some of those
timelines. Okay, והאי מאוחר הוא? V'hai m'uchar hu?
So then we're going to say that if it's, that it's a
שטר מאוחר shtar m'uchar because
if you're not giving the complete year, you've left off a thousand
years. So it sounds, so then if you're going to mention, right,
depending on how the שטר shtar is written, it could be ambiguous
whether it was from now or for a thousand years from now.
Okay, אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, בגולה אין מונין אלא למלכי
יוונים בלבד. Ba-golah ein monin ela l'malchei Yevanim bilvad.
No, in גלות, galut, in outside of the land of Israel, certainly,
the thing that we're counting from is from מלכות יוונים. Malchut Yevanim.
We count from the Greek empires. הוא סבר דחויי קא מדחי ליה.
Hu savar dichuyei ka madchei lei.
He says that דחויי קא מדחי ליה dichuyei ka madchei lei like
that we're pushing it off, meaning you
mean he means you think it was a bad answer?
Right, he thought it was a bad answer. So he says נפק
דק ואשכח. Nafak dak v'ashkach.
So he went out and chased after him and tried to clarify
the point. דתניא בגולה אין מונין אלא למלכי יוונים בלבד. De-tanya ba-golah
ein monin ela l'malchei Yevanim bilvad. So he said, is it really
true that this ברייתא braita teaches that we only count according to
the Greek years? אמר רבינא מתניתין נמי דיקא דתנן Amar Ravina matnitin
nami dika detnan
and even from the משנה Mishnah you could infer this. We often
see things like this: there's a ברייתא braita that says something explicitly
and there's a משנה Mishnah that says it implicitly. That was the
great skill of אילפא. Ilfa. If we remember the גמרא Gemara compares
the prowess of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and אילפא. Ilfa. And אילפא
Ilfa was maybe even greater than רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan but he
decided to leave the בית מדרש. Beit Midrash. But every time they
would quote him a ברייתא, braita, he could say tell me the
ברייתא, braita, I'll tell you where it is in the משנה Mishnah
implicitly. And רב ראובן מרגליות Rav Reuven Margolios in his introduction to
his מרגליות הים Margolios Ha-Yam on סנהדרין Sanhedrin has a beautiful discussion
there of the character of אילפא Ilfa and how, you know, that
אילפא Ilfa had to go earn a living and he left the
בית מדרש Beit Midrash and to not, you know, balancing work and
תורה Torah study.
Okay, what's interesting that it says in the diaspora it's count according
to the Greek years. Right, it's like taking on the conqueror's framework.
Right, you're
now in the diaspora, you're outside of your land.
If you're in Israel, there's more of a fidelity to our government,
our system, our history, our culture. If we're in גולה, golah, that
reality is that we are surrounded by a culture which is not
our own.
But wasn't it the Romans by that time? So why don't they
do it based on the Romans?
Because even the Romans were, we're going to see here the next
part of the סוגיא sugya is going to begin with a description
of how the Romans basically got stole everything from the Greeks. They
had their Greek alphabet and Greek language. The Greek, the Hellenistic culture,
especially in the eastern Mediterranean, was primarily still a Greek culture, not
a Latin culture. There's a whole discussion of
translation, how much did the Roman Empire use Greek as a lingua
franca and not Latin, and Latin was only for bureaucratic things. So
there's a lot of sense that the Greek influence was still very
pervasive even for hundreds of years after the collapse of the Greek
empires.
Okay, so says the משנה. Mishnah. So אמר רבינא מתניתין נמי דיקא
דתנן. Amar Ravina matnitin nami dika detnan. The משנה Mishnah says באחד
בניסן ראש השנה למלכים ולרגלים. Be-echad b'Nisan Rosh Hashanah l'melachim v'laregalim. So
the משנה Mishnah says that ניסן Nisan is ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
for kings and for holidays. ואמרינן למלכים. Va-amrinan l'melachim. So it sounds
like we should count the rule of kings, how many years have
passed for the rule of a king from ניסן, Nisan, not from
תשרי. Tishrei. למאי הלכתא? L'mai hilchata? So what הלכה halacha is this
coming to teach? אמר רב חסדא לשטרות. Amar Rav Chisda l'shtarot.
It comes
to teach that when we count for שטרות shtarot as well, the
year should advance one year at ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. ניסן. Nissan.
ותנן באחד בתשרי ראש השנה לשנים ולשמיטין, ve-tnan be-ehad be-Tishrei Rosh ha-Shanah
li-shanim u-li-shmitin, but the same משנה mishna says that תשרי Tishrei is
ראש השנה Rosh ha-Shanah
for years and for שמיטה shmita years, ואמרינן לשנים, ve-amrinan li-shanim, it
sounds like it says for years, למאי הלכתא? le-mai hilkhata?
So what does that teach the הלכה? halakha? ואמר רב חסדא לשטרות.
ve-amar Rav Hisda li-shtarot. So it sounds like that should count for
שטרות shtarot and רב חסדא Rav Hisda is the one saying both.
רב חסדא Rav Hisda interpreted two different clauses in the same משנה
mishna perhaps at different times referring to the same thing, so we
have a problem.
So קשיא שטרות אהדדי, kashya shtarot a-hadadei, so the two teachings about
שטרות shtarot contradict, ומשנינן כאן למלכי ישראל כאן למלכי עובדי כוכבים. u-meshaninan
kan le-malkhei Yisrael kan le-malkhei ovdei kokhavim.
The difference is that Jewish kings count their rule from years from
ניסן Nissan and non-Jewish kings will count their rule from תשרי. Tishrei.
That's sort of a general sense that we have already from last
week's פרשה parsha and from we talk about this a lot at
ראש השנה Rosh ha-Shanah time that the Jewish year starts in ניסן
Nissan but a universal human human year starts in תשרי. Tishrei. תשרי
Tishrei is when we, you know, we say the בריאת העולם briat
ha-olam and the Jewish people were created as a nation in ניסן,
Nissan, things like that. So that's a distinction. Of course, it gets
complicated when you're trying to say what year is it or who
how many years did such and such king reign and you count
even one month as a full year when it was before ראש
השנה Rosh ha-Shanah and things like that, it gets a little bit
tricky.
So what would they do in a שטר? shtar? They'd say
whatever it is, four hundred years since the Greek whatever, which is
the tenth year of King Ashurbanipal? Like what would they do? Or
would they think all these years?
Probably one or the other, maybe would have both, I'm not sure.
In in modern time, you will say whatever it is today, ט
בשבט, Tet be-Shevat, blah blah blah. Right. Twenty-fifth of January.
Right.
That's not my question.
My question is in a historical
שטר. shtar. From what I understand, from what I've seen of archaeological
finds of business contracts, they
the dating is often not so precise necessarily. It may have the
date of the month, but not necessarily the year, or if it
has a year, it would be counted either according to the king
or according to the whatever.
No, because here we just went
out by saying we're trying to establish a convention. We're trying to
establish a convention, but the fact is that maybe there wasn't such
a rigid convention.
I'm sure there are other people who know much more about this.
Wait, wait, דף daf and a half, we've been saying that it's
for the start of the Seleucid dynasty. Yeah, but now we're saying
it's for the kings.
No, so meaning when we're meaning but that's the kings. Counting according
to the kings is counting according in this case to the Seleucid
dynasty. We're saying מלכי עובדי כוכבים, malkhei ovdei kokhavim, מלכי עובדי כוכבים
malkhei ovdei kokhavim means מנין שטרות, minyan shtarot, means מלכי יונים. malkhei
Yevanim. That's what we...
So they're not saying that
we're not going to actually say it's the third year of the
reign of Antoninus, we're not going to say that. We're just going
to say it's five hundred years since since מנין שטרות. minyan shtarot.
Yeah. It becomes sort of a rigid convention because it's easier, especially
if you have Jews living in a Persian empire and in a
Roman empire it gets confusing if the whole Jewish people can't have
a unified calendrical system. So that helps.
Okay, fine. רב
חסדא לשטרות, Rav Hisda li-shtarot, ומשנינן כאן למלכי ישראל כאן למלכי עובדי
כוכבים. u-meshaninan kan le-malkhei Yisrael kan le-malkhei ovdei kokhavim. למלכי עובדי כוכבים
מתשרי מנינן, le-malkhei ovdei kokhavim mi-Tishrei mininan, so for non-Jewish kings we
count from תשרי, Tishrei, ולמלכי ישראל מניסן מנינן, u-le-malkhei Yisrael mi-Nissan mininan,
and for Jewish kings we count from ניסן. Nissan. ואנן השתא מתשרי
מנינן, ve-anan hashta mi-Tishrei mininan, nowadays, meaning now that we're using מנין
שטרות minyan shtarot to count from the Seleucid dynasty, we count from
תשרי. Tishrei. ואי סלקא דעתך מיציאת מצרים מנינן, ve-i salka da-atakh mi-Yetsiat
Mitsrayim mininan, if you would say that we're counting from יציאת מצרים,
Yetsiat Mitsrayim, you רב אחא בר יעקב, Rav Aha bar Yaakov, then
we should have to count from ניסן Nissan because that's a Jewish
count, so it should restart in ניסן, Nissan, מניסן. mi-Nissan. בעינן למימנא?
be-inan le-mimna? אלא לאו שמע מינה למלכי יונים מנינן שמע מינה. ella
lav shema mina le-malkhei Yevanim mininan shema mina. So
the conclusion of this whole discussion is that we count according to
the number of years since the Seleucid
dynasty,
the גויש goyish system.
The גויש goyish system, more or less, which is interesting to consider
that now I think most Jewish שטרות shtarot that we have, a
גט, get, a כתובה, ketubah, all sorts of things, won't use מנין
שטרות minyan shtarot anymore. We use מנין
בריאת העולם. minyan briat ha-olam. I don't think they do both, certainly
not in a כתובה, ketubah, though I have seen some כתובות ketubot
that still would do a מנין שטרות, minyan shtarot, but it's an
interesting point.
So why did we change?
Why did we change? Because at some point after fifteen hundred years,
two thousand years since the Seleucids, people said why are we doing
this anymore? There hasn't been a Seleucid dynasty. So they changed the
convention everywhere,
possibly because of a Kabbalistic sort of influence and interest in when
the world was created, especially around the beginning of the sixth millennium
of the מנין בריאת העולם, minyan briat ha-olam, which is around the
year let's do quick math in our
heads... eight hundred years ago. Right, it's roughly was in
twelve forty, twelve forty, twelve forty-one, so around that
time there was a Kabbalistic fervor around... What?
You have a quick question? Yeah, yeah, so you're saying that in
our standard כתובות Ketubot and גיטין, Gittin, that no one does typically
the 2000, whatever it is?
I don't think they do 2000 at all. If they would do
anything, they would do בריאת העולם Briat HaOlam and מנין שטרות, Minyan
Shtarot, I think. You can't ask me on גיטין, Gittin, I also
don't know that. So, okay. יום גינוסיא של מלכיהם. Yom Ginussia shel
Malcheihem. So, מאי ויום גינוסיא
של מלכיהם? Mai ve'Yom Ginussia shel Malcheihem? What is this יום גינוסיא?
Yom Ginussia? So, אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, יום שמעמידים בו
עובדי כוכבים את מלכם. Yom she'ma'amidin bo ovdei kochavim et malkam.
It's the coronation day. What? Inauguration day, coronation day of the new
king. It's important to note in the Roman Empire, the Caesar was
not exactly what we would consider a dynastic
hereditary king type of ruler. The emperor was officially appointed by the
Senate until the Senate was dissolved, but at this period, and so
there was a whole sense that, right, it's מעמידים בו עובדי כוכבים
את מלכם, ma'amidin bo ovdei kochavim et malkam, that there is some
sort of an electoral process by which the nation picks the king,
which is actually very interesting. Okay, והתניא יום גינוסיא ויום שמעמידים בו
את מלכם. ve'ha tanya Yom Ginussia ve'Yom she'ma'amidin bo et malkam.
So doesn't it, but we have a ברייתא Baraita that lists both
of those as two separate events? לא קשיא הא דידיה הא דבריה.
la kashya ha didey ha dibrey. One is a reference to the
king himself and one is the coronation day of the son. That
is, while the king is still alive, they could have a coronation
day to name the son as the prince regent or something like
that, that he'll be the heir apparent, and they would have a
coronation for that as well. ומי מוקמי מלכא בר מלכא? u'mi mukmi
malka bar malka? Is it really true that the Romans would ever
appoint a king the son of a king? That is because it
was this electoral process and because there was so much political infighting
in the Roman Empire, it was rare that the Caesar would be
the son of the previous Caesar. והתניא רב יוסף, ve'ha tanya Rav
Yosef, הנה קטנתיך בגוים. hineh katanatiticha bagoyim.
There's a prophecy in עובדיה. Ovadia. עובדיה, Ovadia, we know is a
reference to the kingdom of אדום, Edom, which in the חז"ל Chazal
is certainly understood to be the Roman Empire. And the prophecy says
that I, God says, I have made you the smallest among the
nations. That is, Rome obviously was a very great nation, populous and
in terms of the extent of their empire, but in other ways,
they're meant to be seen as very small. שאין מושיבין מלך בן
מלך. she'ein moshivin melech ben melech. One of the ways in which
they're considered to be a weak nation is that they were never
able to establish a dynastic rule of kings. Each Caesar was appointed
independently.
So of course, because of our פסוק, pasuk, which we choose to
interpret this way,
it
must mean that in practice, well, we're going to see it's rejected.
So, בזוי אתה מאד bezuy ata me'od שאין לכם לא כתב ולא
לשון, she'ein lachem lo ktav ve'lo lashon, but further, so what does
the פסוק pasuk mean, בזוי אתה מאד, bezuy ata me'od, you're very
denigrated because they don't have their own alphabet, they stole the alphabet
from the Greeks, ולא לשון, ve'lo lashon, and they don't even really
have their own language because they use Greek as their lingua franca,
especially in the Eastern Empire.
Clearly they had their own language.
Clearly they had their own language. The alphabet was very similar to
the Greek alphabet. Yeah, we know that for sure.
They have Roman numerals, I thought.
Yeah, that, but they got the alphabet is mostly borrowed from the
Greek alphabet. Not all of it, but most of it. But there
was a lot of overlap, meaning the Romans, to be cultured in
Rome was to study Greek philosophy and Greek literature and Greek plays
and things like that.
So maybe, no, I was going to say like America and England,
whatever. Like there's examples in history
of a conquering nation and then you absorb their culture and their,
right. It's part, I mean that was part of the success of
Rome as they said, we're the great military power, we have a
great bureaucratic governmental power, but they recognized or they were felt an
inferiority complex to the Greeks who had preceded them in terms of
music and art and philosophy and literature and things like that. Okay,
אלא מאי יום גינוסיא? ela mai Yom Ginussia? So what is יום
גינוסיא? Yom Ginussia? יום הלידה. Yom Ha'leda. It's the birthday, the king's
birthday. Okay, והתניא ve'ha tanya יום גינוסיא ויום הלידה, Yom Ginussia ve'Yom
Ha'leda, that
references both the יום גינוסיא Yom Ginussia and the birthday. לא קשיא
הא דידיה הא דבריה. la kashya ha didey ha dibrey. No, one
is a reference to the king and one is a reference to
the king's son.
King makes a big birthday for his son. We know there are
other משניות Mishnayot that reference the day that the first shaving day,
the Romans made a very big deal for a young man. Something
like an אפשערן, opsherin, probably around age of 12 or 13.
Also just important to note, who's the only character in the תורה
Torah to celebrate a birthday? יום הולדת את פרעה. Yom Huledet et
Paroh. So it's very... good birthday wishes to whomever has their birthday
today. Exactly. Well, that's why we don't make such a big deal
of birthdays in Judaism. Okay. We have something called a בר מצוה.
Bar Mitzvah. He also had a בר מצוה *bar mitzvah*. Yes, something,
something else. Okay. Exactly. Well, that's why we don't make such a
big deal of birthdays in Judaism. Okay. והתניא יום גינוסיא שלו ויום
גינוסיא של בנו *Vehatanya yom ginosia shelo veyom ginosia shel bno*. So
but we have another ברייתא *braisa* that references both the יום גינוסיא
*yom ginosia* of the king and of his son, ויום הולדת שלו
ויום הולדת של בנו *veyom hahuledet shelo veyom hahuledet shel bno*, and
the birthday, the king's birthday and the prince's birthday. So it doesn't
seem like that's the correct interpretation. אלא מאי יום גינוסיא *Ela mai
yom ginosia*? We go back to our first attempt, what does it
mean יום גינוסיא *yom ginosia*? יום שמעמידים בו מלכא *yom shema'amidin bo
malka*. It's the coronation day. ולא קשיא הא דידיה והא דבריה *Velo
kashya ha deidei veha debrei*. And there's no contradiction that it mentions
both יום מעמידים בו מלכא *yom ma'amidin bo malka* and יום גינוסיא
*yom ginosia* because one is the day of the king's coronation and
one is the day of the prince-regent's coronation. ואי קשיא לך דלא
מוקמי מלכא בר מלכא *Ve'i kashya lach delo mokmi malka bar malka*.
If you're going to ask me about the fact that the Romans
never appoint as a king the son of the king, על ידי
שאילה מוקמינן *al yedei she'eila mokminan*.
If the emperor makes a request that his son fill his role
then they could. And now we're going to have a story from
אנטונינוס Antoninus *Antoninus* talking with רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi. *Rabbi
Yehuda HaNasi* because the first example is כגון אסוירוס בר אנטונינוס Antoninus
*kegon Asverus bar Antoninus*. This is the, so after the death of
אנטונינוס Antoninus *Antoninus* Pius, there were his two adopted sons, Marcus Aurelius
and Lucius Severus ruled as co-emperors. And then Severus
died and then Marcus Aurelius ruled as emperor alone.
So אסוירוס בר אנטונינוס Antoninus *Asverus bar Antoninus*, there was like a
special request that אנטונינוס Antoninus *Antoninus* had to make that his other
son would get to join Marcus Aurelius. Presumably there's an assumption Marcus
Aurelius was more capable or more qualified for that job in some
way. I don't know exactly.
So that's who we're talking about. דמלך *demalach*. So because he became
the emperor. אמר ליה amar leh, אנטונינוס Antoninus לרבי *Amar lei Antoninus
leRabbi*. אנטונינוס Antoninus *Antoninus* said to רבי Rebbi, יהודה הנשיא *Rabbi Yehuda
HaNasi*: בעינא דימלוך אסוירוס ברי תחותי *ba'ina deyimloch Asverus bri tichotai*. I
want my son אסוירוס *Asverus* to be the king after me. ותתעביד
טבריה קלוניא *vetit'avid Tiveriya koloniya*. And that טבריה *Tiveriya* should be given
a remission on its taxes. The problem is ואי אימא להו חדא
עבדי *ve'i eima lehu chada avdi*. If I ask the Senate to
do one of those two things they'll do it for me. תרתי
לא עבדי *tartei lo avdi*, but they're not going to do both
for me. So he says רבי Rebbi *Rabbi*, I really want to
give you a break in your taxes but I also really want
my son to be the emperor after me. So I have to
pick. So רבי Rebbi, יהודה הנשיא *Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi* is much smarter
than אנטונינוס Antoninus *Antoninus*. אייתי גברא ארכביה אחיבריה *Aitei gavra arkibei achavreia*.
He brought before him a person riding piggyback on somebody else's shoulders.
ויהב ליה יונה לעילא בידיה *Veyahav lei yona le'eila bidei*. He put
a dove into the hands of the one sitting on top, בידיה
*bidei*, in his hands. ואמר ליה לתתא אימר לעילא למיפרח מידיה יונה
*Ve'amar lei letata eimar le'eila limifrach midei yona*. He told the lower
one to tell the upper one to let the bird fly out
of his hands, מידיה יונה *midei yona*. אמר amar, שמע מינה הכי
קאמר לי *Amar shema mina hachi ka'amar li*. So אנטונינוס Antoninus
*Antoninus* inferred from this that what רבי Rebbi. *Rabbi* was telling him
is: את בעי מנייהו דאסוירוס ברי ימלוך תחותי *at ba'ei mineihu deAsverus
bri yimloch tichotai*. I should ask the Senate to appoint אסוירוס *Asverus*
my son as the emperor. ואימא ליה לאסוירוס דתתעביד טבריה קלוניא *Ve'eima
lei leAsverus detit'avid Tiveriya koloniya*. And then you should request from your
son once he's been made the emperor in your place that he
should give a tax remission to טבריה *Tiveriya*. Okay. Did you have
a question?
Yeah. I have a note here from the דורות הראשונים *Doros HaRishonim*.
It says they identify אנטונינוס Antoninus *Antoninus* as the Roman emperor Marcus
Aurelius אנטונינוס Antoninus *Antoninus*. He ruled from 161 to 180 CE.
And in
the course of his travels he met רבי Rebbi *Rabbi* and they
had a long friendship. Okay. I'm not sure they're conflating the two
words Marcus Aurelius אנטונינוס *Antoninus*.
Well so he took his father's name as a patronymic.
Oh I see what you're saying. He was the son of אנטונינוס
*Antoninus*.
He was the adopted son of אנטונינוס *Antoninus*, right.
But he was, but he was Marcus Aurelius.
I'm not sure.
Between the dating it gets a little complicated. I think אנטונינוס *Antoninus*
Pius was emperor until like
150 or something like that. So he could have been friends with
רבי Rebbi *Rabbi* as a young man. I don't know. I don't
know who was when. Obviously I don't know factually, historically from the
Roman perspective if any of this ever happened. Our tradition tells us
that it happened.
So I don't know.
Sometimes when you get down to the details which king was which,
it's hard to pin down.
Okay. So another story. אמר ליה amar lei, מצערין לי חשובי רומאי
*Amar lei metza'arin li chasuvei Romai*. The dignitaries of Rome are giving
me a hard time. מעייליה לגינא *Ma'ayilei legina*. He went to the
garden. כל יומא עקר ליה פוגלא ממשרא קמיה *Kol yoma akar lei
pugla mimashra kamei*. He took up a פוגלא *pugla*, is what, a
radish? He plucked a radish every day. אמר שמע מינה הכי קאמר
לי *Amar shema mina hachi ka'amar li*. He said to himself, it's
like what רבי Rebbi. *Rabbi* is telling me: את קטול חד חד
מינייהו ולא תתגרי בהו בכולהו *at ktol chad chad mineihu velo titgari
behu bechulhu*. Kill them off one at a time, the people who
are giving you a hard time. Don't kill them all at once
because then they're going to overreact and there's going to be some
kind of a revolt. Okay. ולימא ליה מימר בהדיא *Velima lei meimar
behadya*. We're flipping the דף *daf*, flipping the דף *daf* עמוד ב
*amud beis*. ולימא ליה מימר בהדיא *Velima lei meimar
behadya*. Why couldn't רבי Rebbi have just told Antoninus that in public?
So אמר, שמעי בי חשובי רומי ומצערו ליה. sham'ei bei chashuvei romi
umatzaru lei.
He said to himself, oh, if the Roman dignitaries hear about this,
they're going to give me a hard time. But ולימא ליה בלחש,
v'leima lei belachash, he could have whispered it to him? משום דכתיב
כי עוף השמים יוליך את הקול. mishum d'chtiv ki of hashamayim yoliche
et hakol. We have a פסוק pasuk from קהלת Kohelet that even
when you whisper something, sometimes the secret can get out. So you
have to say something in a coded message or in an obscured
way so that to prevent rumors from getting out. As Benjamin Franklin
said, three can keep a secret if two of them are dead.
It's very difficult once you tell one person, you don't know what's
going to be the future of your secrecy.
ומילי דאמרי u'milatze d'amri סודא לשנים סודא ללבבות, soda lishnayim sodei l'vavot,
סודא לשלושה סודא לרחובות. sodei l'shlosha soda l'rchovot.
But even for שנים, shnayim, meaning even two, even שנים shnayim could
be difficult.
It doesn't, it depends. It depends what you tell, who you tell.
You tell two people it's a secret
of the heart. Three people it's a secret of the street. Right,
but that's right. So at least here we're suspicious even one person
telling another person something, especially something with a political intrigue going on.
כי עוף השמים יוליך את הקול, ki of hashamayim yoliche et hakol,
the birds are going to spread the news, who knows, right? Parrots
can repeat things that they overhear in the kitchen all the time,
right? הוה ליה ההוא ברתא דשמה גירא דעבדה
איסורא. hava lei hahu barta d'shema Gira d'avda issura. So
Antoninus had a daughter who was doing איסורים. issurim. It sounds like
the reference here is that she was sexually promiscuous or something like
that. שדר ליה גרגירא, shadar lei gargira,
so he sent to him a גרגירא, gargira, גרגירא gargira is some
kind of like a wild mustard plant, but it's like a pun
on the word גירא. Gira. שדר ליה כוסברתא, shadar lei kusbarta, he
sent him back כוסברתא, kusbarta, כוסברתא kusbarta is the cabbages or something.
No, כוסברתא kusbarta at least now, כוסברתא kusbarta
not
parsley.
Oh, cilantro. Coriander. Yeah, right, right, כוסברתא, kusbarta, right. But it's a
pun because כוס ברתא kus barta is like kill your daughter basically.
שדר ליה כרתי, shadar lei karti, he sent him leeks, leeks, like
to say כרתי karti like I'm going to cut her off, like
כרת, karat, like I'll cut off her head. שלח ליה חסא, shalach
lei chasa, he sent him back lettuce to say חסא chasa like
no you should forgive
her, like לחוס lachus like to have compassion on her. Some kind
of a strange back and forth between Antoninus and רבי, Rebbi they're
just sending each other vegetables but they understand it as a message.
Now this is like that old joke, right, about the rabbi and
the priest are having the silent debate and the priest takes the
apple and he goes like this and he points, right, all of
those things. And so when you're having a non-, when you have
a coded conversation but you if you interpret the code in two
different ways, who knows what Antoninus thought רבי rabbi, and he were
exchanging vegetables, they're just sending each other their lunch, I don't know.
So at least from our perspective it sounds like it makes sense.
Okay. כל יומא הוה שדר ליה דהבא פריכא במטראתא וחיטי
אפומייהו. kol yoma hava shadar lei dahava paricha b'matrata v'chiti apu maihu.
I'm going to get the English to help us with this one
second. Some of these I got to tell you are a little
bit challenging, one
second, right, I just wanted to get the book, it's just going
to make it much smoother for me to finish everything in the
correct time, one second, okay fine.
Okay,
כל
יומא הוה שדר ליה דהבא פריכא
במטראתא וחיטי אפומייהו. kol yoma hava shadar lei dahava paricha b'matrata v'chiti
apu maihu. He would send him, that is Antoninus would send to
רבי, Rebbi. a bag of gold like in powders, in granules, so
it would be like the texture of wheat kernels, but he put
wheat on the top to cover up the top so that anybody
who opened up the bag would think it was just wheat, it
wasn't a bag of gold. Obviously gold is much denser than wheat
so it would be very difficult to imagine how anyone lifting this
would not think that it was very heavy, that there was something
was strange going on
in a bag. אמר להו אמטיו חיטי לרבי, amar lehu amtchu chiti
l'Rebbi, he said bring the wheat to רבי. Rebbi, אמר ליה רבי,
amar lei Rebbi, רבי Rebbi said back to him, לא צריכנא, la
tzrichna, I don't need it. Why are you sending me all this
money? אית לי טובא, it li tuva, I have plenty of money,
I'm rich enough, right? Like יעקב Yaakov and עשו, Eisav, right, of
course this is יעקב Yaakov and עשו Eisav again. עשו Eisav sends
back and he says יש לי רב yesh li rav and he
says יש לי כל, yesh li kol, right, so this is the
same kind of dynamic. אמר והבו למן דבתרך דיהבו לבתראי דאתו בתרך,
amar v'habu l'man
d'batrach d'yehavu l'batrai d'atu batrach, you should have the gold now so
that the people who come after you will be able to pay
off the people who come after me,
basically.
Okay, ודאתו מנייכו נפיקו עלייהו, u'd'atu minaichu neipoku alaichu, and the people
who come after you will be able to pay the taxes using
this money. Okay, הוה ליה ההוא נקרותא דהוה אלייהו מביתיה לבית רבי.
hava lei hahu nakruta d'hava alaichu m'beitei l'veit Rebbi. So there was
a tunnel going from Antoninus's house to רבי's Rebbi house. Now if
Antoninus
was living in Rome... So I don't know, it could still be
a long tunnel. Who knows? Magic tunnel. I don't know. Okay.
Just so that they could study Torah.
He could study Torah. At least they had a good friendship. I
don't know whether אנטונינוס was studying תורה, Torah, but they were at
least talking politics. Okay. כל יומא הוה מייתי תרי עבדי, kol yoma
hava maite tray avdai, every day he would bring two slaves with
him. חד אקטליה אבבא דבי רבי, cha ad kitla abava d'vei Rebbi,
one he would kill at the doorway to רבי'ס Rebbi's house, וחד
אקטליה אבבא דביתיה, vechad kitla abava d'beiteh, and one he would kill
at the doorway of his own house. Meaning he would bring the
two slaves to escort him along the way, but then he had
to kill them so that they wouldn't reveal the secret that he
was going to learn with רבי. Rebbi So אמר ליה, בעידנא דאתינא
לא נשכח גבר קמך. be'idana d'atena la nishkach gevar k'mach. He said,
when I come visit you, there shouldn't be any people here because
I want it to stay a secret.
There's a story like the Egyptian pharaohs who would kill the designers
of the
pyramids or something so that no one would know. Something like that.
Right. There is this sense of security. Right. Obviously, if every day
you're killing off your bodyguard, you have to wonder who's going to
want the job eventually, right? But it wasn't a free choice.
It was certainly was not.
They're עבדים, avadim, right? They're slaves. So, but that's part of, like,
we can and also we're sort of getting into the mindset of
אנטונינוס a little bit, like what, how does he think? His daughter
has a bad reputation, he's going to kill her, right? All of
these little pieces of the story.
Right.
He kills off all of his slaves. So he's still being portrayed
as this gruff,
crude Roman character, Machiavellian kind of character, but רבי Rebbi, still has
a good relationship with him either because it's good for the Jews
or for some other reason, I don't
know. Okay. So
יומא חד, yoma chad, אשכחיה לרבי חנינא בר חמא דהוה יתיב. ashkcheih
l'Rabbi Chanina bar Chama d'hava yativ. One day when אנטונינוס came to
visit, he noticed that רבי חנינא בר חמא Rabbi Chanina bar Chama
was there visiting with רבי Rebbi as well, but he had told
him I don't want anybody here when I come to visit. אמר
ליה אמינא לך בעידנא דאתינא לא נשכח גבר קמך. amar leh amina
lach be'idana d'atana la nishkach gevar k'mach. Didn't I tell you that
when I come to visit there shouldn't be any people here? אמר
ליה לית דין בר איניש. amar leh leit dein bar inish. He's
not a human being, meaning really he's like an angel, he's like,
he's non-human, he's so perfect, he's such an amazing student. So אמר
ליה אימא ליה דההוא עבדא דגני אבבא דקאי וליתי.
eima leh d'hahu avda d'ganei abava
d'kaim v'latei. So אנטונינוס told רבי חנינא בר חמא, Rabbi Chanina bar
Chama, go go tell the slave at the doorway that he should
come, that he should wake up, like as if he was sleeping,
though he had killed him. אזל רבי חנינא בר חמא אשכחיה דהוה
קטיל. azal Rabbi Chanina bar Chama ashkcheih d'havah katil. He found him
that he was dead. אמר היכי אביד? amar heichi avid? Now now
what was it that אנטונינוס was trying to communicate something to him?
Either A, like watch out I'm going to kill you because I
don't want anybody to know the secret. So now he's worried. So
what does he do? What should I do? אי איזיל ואימא ליה
דקטיל. ee ezol ve'eima leh d'katil. If I go and tell him
oh, he's been killed, אין משיבין על הקלקלה. ein meshivin ha-kala'ah. You're
not supposed to report bad news to people, because he doesn't know
that he had killed him himself. אשבקיה ואיזיל. ashvakeih ve'ezol.
Should I just leave? ואיכא מזלזלא במלכותא. ve'ichah mezalzina be-malchuta.
That's going to be seen as disrespectful to the king. בעא רחמי
עליה, ba rachamei alei,
ואחייה ושדריה. ve'achayei ushdarei. He prayed for him, and he brought him
back to life and sent
him. אמר ידענא זוטא דאית
בכו מחיה מתים. amar yadana zuta d'itchu mechayeh metim.
So אנטונינוס said wow, even the least among your students is able
to do מחיה מתים, mechayeh metim, is about to bring the dead
back to life. מיהו בעידנא דאתינא לא נשכחיניש קמך. mihu be'idana d'atana
la nishkachinish k'mach.
But still, I don't want anybody here visiting with you next time
I come to visit. That is great. רבי חנינא בר חמא Rabbi
Chanina bar Chama is a powerful רבי, he has magic powers, but
I don't want people to know about our secret. Okay. כל יומא
הוה משמש ליה לרבי. kol yoma hava meshamesh l'Rebbi.
Every day אנטונינוס would bring food for רבי. He was משמש, meshamesh,
he was like the waiter. Again, it's portraying who's in the power
in this relationship. אנטונינוס is the student of רבי, he's serving him,
he's taking care of him. So מאכליה, machilei, he would bring him
food, ומשקיה, umashkeilei, and he would bring him something to drink. כי
הוה בעי רבי למיסק לפורייה. ki hava baei Rebbi l'misak l'purya. When
רבי would go into his bed, הוה גחין קמי פורייה. hava gachin
kamei purya. He would get, he would bow in front of the
bed as a step to provide a step for רבי to step
into his bed. In the גמרא Gemara in קידושין Kiddushin we see
examples of children doing this to help their parents into bed, which
is seen as a great כיבוד אב ואם. kibbud av va-em. So
this same way אנטונינוס is showing a great כבוד kavod to רבי
יהודה הנשיא.
This story also in the מדרש, Midrash, I don't know whether it's
a מדרש Midrash or whatever, but that
מרדכי Mordechai steps on המן'ס Haman's head to
get advanced.
Right. And המן Haman getting pushed back. Right. So it's similar. It's
very much... self- but it's respectful way. It's a person showing a
lot of care in the service of the person that they're helping.
It's a bit- אמר ליה *Amar lei*: שקי לואי לפורייך *saki lavai
le-puryach*. So he said
like get climb on me to get into your bed. So אמר
*amar*, לאו אורח ארעא לזלזולי במלכותא כולי האי *lav orch arch le-zalzulei
be-malchuta kulei hai*. And Rebbi said I'm not going to stand on
you because you're the Roman Emperor. I can't step on you. You're
the king. It's not appropriate to show disrespect to the king. אמר
*amar*, מי ישימני מצע תחתיך לעולם הבא *mi yesimeni matza tachteicha le-olam
ha-ba*. I hope and pray that in עולם הבא Olam Ha-Ba. *Olam
Ha-ba* I will be your mattress, that is that I would be
of such a level to be to serve you in עולם הבא
Olam Ha-Ba. *Olam Ha-ba*. Obviously the image of one person making themselves
like the mattress is
very graphic sense of how much they're lowering themselves in comparison to
the other person. So אמר ליה *amar lei*, אתינא לעלמא דאתי *atena
le-alma de-atei*, will I be able to enter עולם הבא Olam Ha-Ba
*Olam Ha-ba*? So now he said oh I hope to be your
mattress in עולם הבא Olam Ha-Ba *Olam Ha-ba*, but now he says
am I ever going to be able to get into עולם הבא
*Olam Ha-ba*? אמר ליה *amar lei*, he said back to him, אין
*in*. He said yes you will. So אמר ליה *amar lei*, והכתיב
לא יהיה שריד לבית עשו *ve-haktiv lo yihye sarid le-veit Esav*, doesn't
the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* from עובדיה *Ovadia* say that there will be
no remnant for בית עשו *Beit Esav*? בעושה מעשה עשו *be-oseh ma'aseh
Esav*. No, Rebbi says that only applies to someone who acts like
עשו *Esav*. And you, Antoninus, you've shown yourself to be courteous, you
love תורה Torah *Torah*, you support the Jews, whatever it is, you
don't do מעשה עשו *ma'aseh Esav*. So תניא נמי הכי *tanya nami
hachi*, we have a similar ברייתא *braita*. לא יהיה שריד לבית עשו
*lo yihye sarid le-veit Esav*, the פסוק *pasuk* says there'll be no
remnant for בית עשו *Beit Esav*. יכול לכל *yachol la-kol*, could it
apply to all of the Romans? תלמוד לומר *talmud lomar*, לבית עשו
*le-veit Esav* בעושה מעשה עשו *be-oseh ma'aseh Esav*. It only applies to
those who actually do the actions of עשו *Esav*. אמר ליה *amar
lei*, והכתיב שמה אדום מלכיה וכל נסיאיה *ve-haktiv shama Edom melacheicha ve-chol
nesi'eiha*, but doesn't a פסוק *pasuk* from יחזקאל *Yechezkel* says there will
be destruction for אדום *Edom*, for its kings, and for all of
its princes? אמר ליה *amar lei*, מלכיה ולא כל מלכיה *melacheicha ve-lo
kol melacheicha*. It says its kings but not all the kings. כל
נסיאיה ולא כל שריה *kol nesi'eiha ve-lo kol sareiha*. All of the
princes but not every single one of the officers. Okay, so that
is some of them will still be able to go into עולם
הבא *Olam Ha-ba*. תניא נמי הכי *tanya nami hachi*, מלכיה *melacheicha*, its
kings, ולא כל מלכיה *ve-lo kol melacheicha*, its kings but not all
of its kings. כל נסיאיה ולא כל שריה *kol nesi'eiha ve-lo kol
sareiha*. So מלכיה *melacheicha*, its kings, ולא כל מלכיה *ve-lo kol melacheicha*,
and not all of the kings, פרט לאנטונינוס בר אסוירוס *perat le-Antoninus
bar Asverus*, that refers specifically to Antoninus who served Rebbi. כל נסיאיה
ולא כל שריה *kol nesi'eiha ve-lo kol sareiha*, all of the princes
but not every single one of the officers, פרט לקטיעה בר שלום
*perat le-Kti'a bar Shalom*. It's a reference to קטיעה בר שלום *Kti'a
bar Shalom*. So we're going to have to find out who's קטיעה
בר שלום *Kti'a bar Shalom*. So קטיעה בר שלום מאי הוה *Kti'a
bar Shalom mai havah*, what was the story of קטיעה בר שלום
*Kti'a bar Shalom*? דההוא קיסרא דהוה סני ליהודאי *de-hahu kesara de-hava sani
lihudai*, there was a Roman Emperor who hated the Jews. אמר להו
לחשיבי דמלכותא *amar lehu la-chashivei de-malchuta*, he told the powerful people in
his empire, מי שעלה לו נימא ברגלו *mi she-ala lo nima be-raglo*,
whoever has a
like an ulcer, like like an injury, a wound on his foot.
יקטענה ויחיה או יניחנה ויצטער *yikti'enah ve-yichyeh o yanichenah ve-yitztayer*, should he
cut it off and it would heal, or should he leave it
there and be in pain? אמרו לו *amru lo*, יקטענה ויחיה *yikti'enah
ve-yichyeh*, he should cut it off and let it heal. That is,
so he said, אמר להו קטיעה בר שלום *amar lehu Kti'a bar
Shalom*, so that the implication is that the Jewish people are like
a festering wound on the Roman Empire. And the emperor wants to
cut off the Jewish people so that they should be allowed that
the empire would be allowed to thrive in the absence of the
Jews. There are a lot of obviously foreshadowings here of many other
incidents of
antisemitism, the sense that the Jewish people are sucking the life out
of the country we live in or something like that. It's really
this is a trope that goes back thousands of years. So אמר
להו קטיעה בר שלום *amar lehu Kti'a bar Shalom*, קטיעה בר שלום
*Kti'a bar Shalom* made a suggestion to the king. חדא דלא יכלת
להו לכולהו *chada de-lo yachalt lehu le-kuleihu*, first of all you can't
kill all of them, דכתיב כי כארבע רוחות השמים פרשתי אתכם *dich-tiv
ki ke-arba ruchot hashamayim perashti etchem*. Because first the פסוק *pasuk* from
זכריה *Zecharia* says that God has spread us out with the four
winds. מאי קאמר *mai ka'amar*? What is that saying? אילימא דבדרתהון בארבע
רוחות *ilei-ma de-vadratehon be-arba ruchot*, does it mean that God has scattered
us to the four directions? היי כארבע רוחות *hai ke-arba ruchot*. The
פסוק *pasuk* says כארבע רוחות *ke-arba ruchot*, like the four winds, not
לארבע רוחות *le-arba ruchot*, not into the four directions מיבעי ליה *miba'ei
lei*. אלא כשם שאי אפשר לעולם בלא רוחות *ela keshem she-iy efshar
la-olam belo ruchot*, just like the world can't exist without the winds,
כך אי אפשר לעולם בלא ישראל *kach אי אפשר לעולם בלא ישראל
*kach iy efshar la-olam belo Yisrael*. The world cannot survive without the
Jewish people. ועוד קרו לך מלכותא קטיעא Keti'a *ve-od, karu lach malchuta
keti'a*, and in the future they will call your empire a cut-off
empire. Because if you cut off the Jews like you're cutting off
this ulcer, then you're going to it will be a cut-off empire.
Also of course the name קטיעה בר שלום *Kti'a bar Shalom* is
a play on that as well. We find many times in the
גמרא *Gemara* that people have a name is an allusion to one
of their more famous
teachings. debate among some of the scholars, is it that they were
named after their popular teachings or were that, did they develop their
certain popular teachings based off of their names? There's a kind of
mnemonic, a little ווארט, vort it's always good to have a ווארט
about your own name I guess. Okay, so אמר ליה, the emperor
said to קטיעא בר שלום, Keti'a bar Shalom, אמר מימר שפיר קאמרת,
amar meimar shapir ka'amarta, you said very well, that is you warned
me against this, מיהו כל דנצחי למלכא שדו ליה לקמוניא חלילא, mihu
kol de-natzechi le-malka shadu lei le-kamonia chalila, but anyone who disagrees with
the king has to be thrown into an empty house, or here
they say קמוניא חלילא kamonia chalila a house full of ashes, I
don't know where they get the ashes part, that from רש"י? Rashi?
Yeah, from רש"י, Rashi, that they had, it's some kind of a
punishment. רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel says that it's a furnace to be
burned, that is they're going to punish, they're going to kill you,
they're going to punish you for disagreeing with the king. כד הוו
נקיטין ליה ואזלין, kad hava naktein lei ve-azlin, so when they were
taking קטיעא בר שלום Keti'a bar Shalom and taking him to be
killed, אמרה ליה ההיא מטרוניתא, amrah lei hahi matronita, a wealthy Roman
woman said, ווי לה לאילפא דאזלא בלא מכסא,
vai lah le-ilfa de-azla
be-lo michsa, woe to the one, to the ship that tries to
cross the border without paying the without paying the customs duty, without
paying the
tax. So נפל ארישא דערלתיה קטעה, nafal a-reisha de-arlatei kate'ah, so he
went bent over to his foreskin and he cut it off. Also
the name קטיעא בר שלום, Keti'a bar Shalom, קטיעא to be cut
off, so again there're allusions to the name there as well. That
is, he was some Roman guy, he disagreed with the emperor, he
tried to defend the Jewish people, the Roman emperor rejected his appeal
and he's going to be executed. He says let me at least
go into into death trying in some way to have shown my
commitment to to protect the Jewish people, so he cut off his
foreskin as a sign, somehow a sign of his desire to convert
to
Judaism. אמר יהבית מכסי חליפת ועברית, amar yahavit michsi chalifet va-avarit, he
said I gave my tax, so let me exchange it and enter
in, that is he wants to go into עולם הבא. כי קא
שדו ליה, ki ka shadu lei, and when he was being taken
to be killed, אמר כל נכסי לרבי עקיבא וחביריו, amar kol nichsai
le-Rabbi Akiva ve-chaverav, all of my property should be given to רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and his colleagues. יצא רבי עקיבא ודרש, yatza Rabbi
Akiva ve-darash, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva came out and made a דרשה.
drasha. He said והיה לאהרן ולבניו, ve-hayah le-Aharon u-le-vanav, when it says
about the קרבנות korbanot or about the תרומה terumah of the of
the לחם הפנים, lechem ha-panim, it says מחצה לאהרן ומחצה לבניו, mechetza
le-Aharon u-mechetza le-vanav, half goes to אהרן Aharon and half to go
to all of the other כהנים. kohanim. Therefore רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
himself is claiming for himself half of the inheritance because it says
רבי עקיבא וחביריו, Rabbi Akiva ve-chaverav, so it should go half to
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and half to all of the other rabbis.
Okay. יצאה בת קול ואמרה, yatzah bat kol ve-amrah, a heavenly voice
comes down and says קטיעא בר שלום מזומן לחיי העולם הבא, Keti'a
bar Shalom mezuman le-chayei ha-olam ha-ba, קטיעא בר שלום Keti'a bar Shalom
has been welcomed into עולם הבא. בכה רבי ואמר, bachah Rebbi ve-amar,
and רבי cried and said יש קונה עולמו בשעה אחת, yesh koneh
olamo be-sha'ah achat, there are those who are able to merit עולם
הבא in one act, in one moment, ויש קונה עולמו בכמה שנים,
ve-yesh koneh olamo be-chamah shanim, and for many people it takes their
whole lives, it takes many years. That is, you know, those of
us who work hard, those of us who are dedicated to living
a good life ברוך השם, Baruch Hashem, it's very important and doing
מצוות mitzvot and studying תורה Torah and all of these wonderful things.
At the same time, there're certain people who with such incredible either
martyrdom or demonstration of complete faith or complete תשובה teshuvah or all
sorts of things can earn עולם הבא poof in one moment. Very
very powerful story. So אנטונינוס שמשיה לרבי, Antoneinus shamshiya le-Rebbi, אנטונינוס would
take care of רבי, would be his
waiter. אדרכן שמשיה לרב, Adrachan shamshiya le-Rav, and אדרכן Adrachan who was
the king of Persia was would be the waiter for רב. Rav.
כי שכיב אנטונינוס, ki shakhav Antoneinus, when אנטונינוס died
אמר רבי נתפרדה חבילה, amar Rebbi nitpardah chavilah, רבי as if gave
a דרשה, drasha, a eulogy for him, he said נתפרדה חבילה, nitpardah
chavilah, the bundle has been untied. That is, we had such a
close friendship and now our friendship has been undone. כי שכיב אדרכן,
ki shakhav Adrachan, when אדרכן Adrachan died אמר רב נתפרדה חבילה. amar
Rav nitpardah chavilah. When אדרכן Adrachan died רב Rav announced that the
bundle has been untied, also that our close friendship has been untied
and that he he
mourned mourned that loss. Let's just do a little bit more, we
have a few more minutes. That one of one of my more
famous favorite favorite stories, the story of אונקלוס. Onkelos. We know אונקלוס
Onkelos is the one who translated the תורה Torah into
Aramaic, אונקלוס הגר, Onkelos Ha-Ger, אונקלוס Onkelos himself was a convert. So
אונקלוס בר קלונימוס איגייר, Onkelos bar Kolonimus igayer, אונקלוס Onkelos the son
of קלונימוס Kolonimus converted to Judaism. The name קלונימוס Kolonimus is also
interesting, it means a good name שם טוב. shem tov. There were
many אשכנזי Ashkenazi rabbis coming from Italy and Greece in an early
Middle Ages who had the name קלונימוס. Kolonimus. There was a whole
קלונימוס Kolonimus family. There's one of the פייטנים paytanim is קלונימוס בן
קלונימוס. Kolonimus ben Kolonimus. So very interesting, קלונימוס Kolonimus is just שם
טוב shem tov in
so אונקלוס בר קלונימוס Onkelos bar Kolonimus could also just mean אונקלוס
Onkelos who had a good reputation, he was a בר קלונימוס, bar
Kolonimus, he was a בעל שם טוב, ba'al shem tov, he had
a good name, so it's an interesting point. Okay. שדר קיסר גונדא
shadar keisar gunda שדר קיסר גונדא דרומאי אבתריה. shadar kesar gunda de-romaye
abatre. So the Roman emperor sent a legion of troops after him,
to chase after אונקלוס Onkelos because he had converted. Why would you
be allowed to convert to Judaism? The Jews are this despised people
in the Roman Empire etc. אונקלוס Onkelos obviously is going to merit
to be a great תורה Torah scholar in his own right even
as a convert. So חזר. hadar. So what happened? So the Roman
emperor sent גונדא דרומאי אבתריה. gunda de-romaye abatre. משכנהו בקראי. mashchinehu bikrai.
He enticed them with פסוקים. pesukim. He quoted פסוקים pesukim from the
תורה Torah, to them and what happened? איגייור. igayur. They all converted.
He was able to somehow convince all of these Roman soldiers that
they should be Jewish. So חזר שדר גונדא דרומאי אחרינא אבתריה. hadar
shadar gunda de-romaye achrina abatre. The Roman emperor sent another troop of
soldiers after him. אמר להו לא תימרו ליה ולא מידי. amar lehu
lo temru leh velo midi. You're not allowed to talk with him.
You're not allowed to... don't let him speak to you. כי הוו
שקלו ואזלו. ki havu shaklu ve-azlu. So when they got there, אמר
להו אימא לכו מילתא בעלמא. amar lehu eima lechu milta be-alma. Can
I say just something? Not תורה, Torah I'll just talk, I'm just
going to speak to you just normal worldly matters.
נפוריא נקיט נורא קמי אפיפרופא. niforia nakat nura kamei apipropre. So the
נפוריא niforia holds the torch for the אפיפרופא, apipropre, for a higher
level minister, right? There are lower level officials and there are higher
level officials in the Roman bureaucracy. אפיפוריא לדוכסא. apiforia le-duchasa. And the
אפיפוריא apiforia holds it for the Duke, for the דוכסא. duchasa. דוכסא
להגמונא. duchasa le-hegemona. And the דוכסא duchasa holds it for the governor.
הגמונא לקומא. hegemona le-koma. And the governor holds it for the ruler.
קומא מי נקיט נורא מקמי אינשי. koma mi nakat nura me-kamei inashe.
Does the ruler hold the torch for anyone? No, because he's the
ruler. The people in charge don't have to do the busy work.
אמרו ליה לא. amru leh la. They said he doesn't. אמר להו
הקדוש ברוך הוא נקיט נורא קמי ישראל. amar lehu hakadosh baruch hu
nakat nura kamei yisrael. But God holds the torch for the Jewish
people. דכתיב וה' הולך לפניהם יומם. de-ketiv ve-hashem holech lifneichem yomam. איגייור
כולהו. igayur kulehu. So God holds a torch for the Jewish people
because God provided light for us in the desert in a עמוד
אש וענן. amud esh ve-anan. God provided the cloud of fire for
us and they all converted because they were so impressed by the
level of relationship between God and the Jewish people, that is God
as if humbles God's self in front of us to provide us
with our needs. Actually very powerful imagery to think about. If the,
in this analogy, it sounds like God serves the Jewish people. But
obviously we know that it's a testament for God's ability to provide
that God also cares for us. So it's this kind of complex
dynamic here that he's pointing out. חזר שדר גונדא אחרינא אבתריה. hadar
shadar gunda achrina abatre. So then
the emperor sent another third wave of troops to try to catch
אונקלוס. Onkelos. אמר להו לא תשתעו מידי בהדיה. amar lehu lo tishta-u
midi bahadeih. So he said don't talk with him at all, not
even mundane matters. כי נקטי ליה ואזלי. ki nakti leh ve-azli. When
they got there, חזא מזוזתא דמנחא אפתחא. chaza mezuzata de-mancha apitcha. They
saw the מזוזה mezuzah on the door. אותיב ידיה עליה. otiv yadeih
aleih. And he put his hand on the מזוזה. mezuzah. That is,
this is the origin perhaps of the מנהג minhag to touch the
מזוזה mezuzah when entering or leaving a room to recognize that it's
there, to see the מזוזה, mezuzah, to be reminded what it symbolizes.
So אותיב ידיה עליה ואמר להו. otiv yadeih aleih ve-amar lehu. He
put his hand on the מזוזה mezuzah and said, מאי האי. mai
hai. What's this? אמרו ליה את. amru leh at. You should tell
us what it is. Like we don't know what it is. We're
Romans, who knows what that is. אמר להו מנהגו של עולם. amar
lehu minhago shel olam. The normal practice in the world. מלך בשר
ודם יושב מבפנים ועבדיו משמרים אותו מבחוץ. melech basar va-dam yoshev bifnim
ve-avadav mishamrim oto mibachutz. Normally the king sits indoors and the servants
are on guard duty outside. ואילו הקדוש ברוך
הוא עבדיו מבפנים והוא משמרם מבחוץ. ilu hakadosh baruch hu avadav mibifnim
vehu mishamram mibachutz. God, we live in our houses and we put
something at the doorway that's a symbol of the fact that God
is outside protecting us. That is, the
מזוזה. mezuzah. שנאמר ה' ישמור צאתך ובואך מעתה ועד עולם. shenemar hashem
yishmor tzeitcha u-vo'echa me-atah ve-ad olam. God is the watchman protecting us.
איגייור כולהו. igayur kulehu. So they all converted to Judaism now for
the fourth time,
third time. תו לא שדר בתריה. tu lo shadar batre. He stopped
sending any more soldiers to try to catch אונקלוס. Onkelos. So obviously
there are many other גמרות gemaras about the prowess of אונקלוס, Onkelos,
the significance of the תרגום אונקלוס. Targum Onkelos. Sadly, perhaps, the practice
in most Jewish communities has been discontinued to recite the תרגום Targum
in the תורה Torah. reading as was originally practiced. But we still
use the תרגום Targum regularly. It provides a very deep sense of
understanding of the words of the תורה. Sometimes using a different word,
a subtle hint here and there. There's a lot of scholarship about
how much was the תרגום Targum within the rabbinic project or not.
That is, אונקלוס Onkelos was not a rabbi necessarily. How much was
he aligned with the rabbinic mindset and the rabbinic interpretation of the
פסוקים pesukim or he was more interested in a more literal interpretation
of the פסוקים. pesukim. One of the things the תרגום אונקלוס Targum
Onkelos tries to ignore or avoid is anthropomorphism and anthropopathism on the
part of God. So תרגום אונקלוס Targum Onkelos very often presents an
interpretation, understanding of the פסוקים pesukim which is a more, a more
abstract vision of God. Much more to be studied. Hope everyone has
a wonderful day. Good morning. We continue
our look at the comments of the תרגום אונקלוס Targum Onkelos on
the weekly פרשה. parsha. We are in פרשת ויצא. Parshat Vayetze. And
again we are looking at how the תרגום Targum deals with the
description of God and the relationship between God and man. We look
at the very famous dream of יעקב אבינו, Yaakov Avinu, the סולם,
sulam, the ladder. The פסוק says והנה ה׳ נצב עליו, vehinei Hashem
nitzav alav, and behold ה׳ Hashem was standing over him. Or standing
on it, meaning on the ladder. How does אונקלוס Onkelos translate the
word נצב? nitzav? He translates it as והא יקרא דה׳ מעתד עלוהי,
veha yekara deHashem meatad alohi, and behold the glory of ה׳ Hashem
was stationed above him. Here again, the תרגום Targum avoids saying that
God Himself was standing, which is a physical posture. Instead it is
the יקרא דה׳, yekara deHashem, the glory of God. And the word
נצב, nitzav, standing, is replaced with מעתד, meatad, which means prepared or
stationed or present. This is a classic example of the תרגום Targum
removing any physical description of the רבונו של עולם. Ribono Shel Olam.
Later on, when יעקב Yaakov wakes up from his sleep, he says
אכן יש ה׳ במקום הזה ואנכי לא ידעתי, achen yesh Hashem bamakom
hazeh veanochi lo yadati, surely ה׳ Hashem is in this place and
I did not know it. אונקלוס Onkelos translates this as בקושטא שכינתא
דה׳ שריא באתרא הדין. bekushta shechinta deHashem sharya beatra hadein. In truth
the שכינה, Shechinah, the divine presence of ה׳, Hashem, dwells in this
place. Again instead of saying ה׳ Hashem is in the place, he
says the שכינתא דה׳, shechinta deHashem, the presence of God, dwells in
the place. We see this consistent pattern throughout the תרגום Targum to
preserve the transcendence of God while still acknowledging His involvement in the
world through His כבוד kavod or His שכינה. Shechinah.